A Guide to the Papers of Joseph C. Hutcheson, 1929-1972
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Joseph C. Hutcheson 1929-1972
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9819
13 boxes and one OS box.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Larry M. Jones of Lawrenceville, Virginia, Hutcheson's law partner, gave the papers to the University. They were picked up in Lawrenceville on 22 September 1972.
Biographical/Historical Information
Joseph C. Hutcheson, a native of Boydton, Virginia, followed his father and three of his brothers into the legal profession and public service. Hutcheson was born on July 23, 1906 to Mary Young and Herbert Farrar Hutcheson, clerk of Mecklenburg County. He attended Virginia Episcopal School and received his A.D. and LL.B. degrees from the University of Virginia.
Hutcheson entered legal practice in Lawrenceville, Virginia, and served in the Navy during World War II. In September 1946 Hutcheson was elected Mayor of Lawrenceville and in 1948 he became Commonwealth's Attorney for Brunswick County. He served until 1957 when he was elected to fill the State Senate seat vacated by Governor Albertis Harrison.
Hutcheson remained in the Senate for fourteen years until he was defeated in the 1971 democratic primary by James T. Kenbridge. At the time of his defeat he was Chairman of the Senate Fish and Game Committee and a high ranking member of the committees on Courts of Justice, Education, Finance, Public Instruction, Nominations and Confirmations and Privileges and Elections. He was also on the steering committee of the Democratic caucus. Hutcheson gained recognition in the Senate for his conservative viewpoint, especially with regard to integration of schools, and he was usually identified with the "Byrd wing" of the Commonwealth's Democratic Party. His death followed his defeat by only five months.
Scope and Content
The Hutcheson Papers, 1929-1972, consist of ca. 3 shelf feet pertaining chiefly to Hutcheson's career in the Virginia Senate, 1958-1972. Included are papers dating from the 1930's regarding his years immediately after college and his service in the Navy. The bulk of the political papers is correspondence with the Senator's constituents and with various political figures. There are files of papers and bills from the Senate sessions and from committees on which Hutcheson served.
The papers are valuable for the volume of correspondence between Hutcheson and other members of the State Senate. The greatest value of the papers, however, is the constituents' correspondence. These letters reveal a great deal about the attitude of Southside Virginia on such issues as "liquor by the drink," integration, state aid to private schools, and the state sales tax.
Arrangement
The collection was received with the papers in rough chronological order. They have been rearranged into three series: political correspondence, political papers, and personal. Within each of the series, the material has been arranged chronologically.
Series I
The political correspondence, 1951-1972, deals largely with the opinions of Hutcheson's constituents about the various bills before the Senate. Several of the communities, Chase City, Lawrenceville, and South Hill, had active civic organizations which initiated large letter writing and telegram campaigns. In almost every case there is a carbon reply to the letter.
Series II
Hutcheson's political papers of 1957-1972 have been arranged by committee ad within each committee folder, the material is as chronological as possible. For each committee there are memorandums, correspondence with other senators pertaining to the business of the committee, etc. There are also copies and drafts of bills presented to the committee. Many of these mimeographed bills have hand-written corrections or changes made by Hutcheson. Also there is a general file of bills and memorandums collected during the various sessions of the Senate. Among these there are many legal sheets with notes written by Hutcheson pertinent to the sessions and speeches.
Series III
Hutcheson's personal papers, 1930-1972, include personal letters, and papers from his immediate post college days, the early years of his law practice and his time in the Navy. The letters from his early career, which again usually include both the letter and a carbon of the reply, give the best description of Hutcheson's personality. Some of the correspondence is filled with private jokes, but from the tone and style of these letters, the reader can gain an insight into the type of person Joseph Hutcheson was. The papers from his last years include correspondence regarding his legal practices, some newspapers clippings of important events of the last two decades, and letters of condolence for his brother Sterling's death.
Contents List
- Series I: Political Correspondence, 1951-1972
  - Correspondence 1951-1957 November (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: Senate Campaign 1957 November and December (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1958 January (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1958 February-April (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: Trading Stamps 1958 February-March (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1958 May-1959 November (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1959 December-1961 November (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1961 December-1962 January (Box 2)
  - Correspondence re: Recommendations 1959-1962 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1962 February-1962 March (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1962 April-1963 December (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1964 January-1964 February (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1964 March-1965 November (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1966 January (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1966 February 1-1966 February 18 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1966 February 18-1966 December (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1967 January-1967 December (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1968 January 2-1968 January 19 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1968 January 20-1968 January 31 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1968 February 1-1968 February 13 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1968 February 14-1968 February 29 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 1968 March-1968 December (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1969 January-1969 December (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1970 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1971 January-1972 February (Box 6)
- Series II: Political Papers, 1957-1972
  - Re: Political Campaign, First Term 1957-1959 (Box 7)
  - Campaign form letters and lists 1957-1958 (Box 7)
  - Re: Steering Committee 1958-1967 (Box 7)
  - Re: The Commission on Education 1959 (Box 7)
  - Re: Scholarship recommendations 1959-1970 (Box 7)
  - Re: Senate Sessions 1959-1967 (Box 8)
  - Re: Scholarship Committee 1959-1970 (Box 8)
  - Re: Senate Campaign 1963 (Box 8)
  - Letters of Recommendation 1963-1965 (Box 8)
  - Re: Senate Campaign 1965 (Box 9)
  - Letters of Recommendation 1965-1971 (Box 9)
  - Re: Senate Campaign 1967 (Box 9)
  - Re: Senate Session 1968 (Box 9)
  - Re: Special Session on the Constitution 1969 (Box 10)
  - Re: Reapportionment 1970 (Box 10)
  - Re: Primary 1971 (Box 10)
  - Re: Senate Sessions 1970-1972 (Box 10)
  - Re: Democratic Primary 1971 (Box 10)
  - Speeches and Accompanying Material (Box 11)
- Series III: Personal Papers, 1930-1972
  - Personal papers 1930 January-1933 December (Box 12)
  - Personal papers 1934-1942 (Box 12)
  - General and Armed Services 1942-1945 (Box 12)
  - Legal and Personal 1968 March-1970 December (Box 12)
  - Family Genealogy (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 13)
  - Photographs (Box 13)
  - Certification as practicing attorney, Virginia Board of Law Examiners 1929 July 15 (Oversize OS)
  - Diploma, Bachelor of Laws, University of Virginia 1930 June 10 (Oversize OS)